<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of information, exhortation, and consolation to all such as are distinguished by names of reproach and ignominy ... : containing also, a sober rebuke for former sloathfulness / by John Onley ...</title>
            <author>Onley, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10781</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13002272</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13002272</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96479</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53376)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96479)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 394:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of information, exhortation, and consolation to all such as are distinguished by names of reproach and ignominy ... : containing also, a sober rebuke for former sloathfulness / by John Onley ...</title>
                  <author>Onley, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96479:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE OF INFORMATION, EXHORTATION, AND CONSOLATION.</p>
            <p>To all ſuch as are diſtinguiſhed by Names of <hi>Reproach</hi> and <hi>Ignominy;</hi> Nevertheleſs, retaining the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of a <hi>good</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards <hi>God</hi> and <hi>all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing alſo, A <hi>Sober</hi> REBUKE for <hi>former Sloathfulneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Onley,</hi> a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> at Sign of the <hi>Elephant</hi> and <hi>Caſtle,</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96479:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96479:2"/>
            <head>An <hi>EPISTLE</hi> of <hi>Information, Exhortation,</hi> and <hi>Conſolation</hi> to all ſuch as are diſtinguiſhed by Names of Reproach, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O all the Children of God, through Faith and Obedience of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, of what Sect, and by what Name ſoever, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced, dignified, or diſtinguiſhed; <hi>Grace, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> from God our Father, and the Lord Jeſus; With all Spiritual Wiſdom, Strength, Valour, Stability, Patience, Selfdenyal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to you be continued, multiplied and encreaſed; that as on the one hand the Nobleneſs of our Extraction, and moſt Magnificent Poſſeſſion, and yet greater and far more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Right in Reverſion, may make us elevate our Minds in the higheſt Region, above that groſs and earthly Body, that the black Monarchy of the Prince of Darkneſs is erected in, &amp; the poor blind World is benighted with, and captivated by, ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and utterly contemning thoſe earthly Pleaſures and faint Conceptions the Earthly Mind is forming to it ſelf, to take Comfort from, that ſhall ſhortly be ingloriouſly daſh'd and precipited, being <hi>Expiring Glories;</hi> whilſt we, moving in our own Sphear, beyond and above their Region, may be without fear of being Let by their faint Oppoſition, go ſafely on from <hi>ſtrength to ſtrength, till we all appear before our God in Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet on the other hand, Conſidering, how unworthily we have walk'd of this Vocation, and unſutable to this Profeſſion, and unbeſeeming the Children of ſo high a Father, and Heirs of ſuch a Glory, though we were taken from Priſon, Death and Condemnation, and raiſed undeſervedly to ſuch an Eternal weight of Glory, yet have we grieved the Spirit of our God,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96479:3"/>by our eſtrayings from him; from the ſight of which (which I ſhall in a few words preſent to my ſelf and you) ſhame, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and confuſion of face lies before us; yet through a right uſe of it, we may be bettered by it, when we have ſeen it, and have ſmarted for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What a deal of Ruſt, Droſs, and Corrupted matter hath contracted it ſelf to us, by our Motion through various Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, even to the provoking of the Lord to ariſe, and ſhew his Diſpleaſure againſt us, by the Symptoms of ſome ſtraits ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching near us, that are the beſt and only Remedies for us, as of old, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in a waſte howling Wilderneſs, in a Land of Deſarts and Pits, and the ſhadow of Death, ſhe was then <hi>Holineſs to the Lord;</hi> but when to crown all their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with ſignal Mercies, the Lord brought them into Houſes that they did not build, and Vineyards that they did not plant, how quickly was thoſe occaſions of Praiſe, turned into a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Apoſtacy from the Father of thoſe Mercies? Shall we need to parallel our Conditions, our former Egyptian ſlavery, with God's eminent Deliverance, by the out-ſtretched Arm of his Power and Providence, with our yearnings of Spirit then after him is yet memorable? and for our after-declinations, we may it's probable, have it ſo legible, that we may run and read our <hi>Sin</hi> in our <hi>Puniſhment:</hi> There is a Judgment begun, and it will go round; the Furnace is preparing, and that Fire therein will be that Proving, that will manifeſt the Verity of each man's building, only the Refined Gold will remain, and it's the Droſs alone we ſhall loſe, and by that Loſs become Rich; though the Sinners in <hi>Sion</hi> be afraid, and fearfulneſs ſurpriſing the hearts of the Hypocrites; our number being thereby leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened, and much of that bulk we made a ſhew of in our ſelves being conſumed, yet ſhall we be not thereby weakned; But Oh how mighty! Oh how great! Oh how ſtrong ſhall we be by that Loſs, that Little, and thoſe Few that will be left, ſtanding by it ſelf, will exceed even it ſelf as it ſtood in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the reſt? why then ſhould we ſtand afraid of that Poverty by which we become rich, or that Loſs by which we get gain?</p>
            <p n="2">2. What a Stir and Commotion, and Hurli-burly hath been
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96479:3"/>raiſed in our Souls? partly by falſe and contrary Intereſts we had eſpouſed to our ſelves, partly by our various Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Helps and Reliefs, to ſecure them to us (having plodded on in a heartleſs, lifeleſs Profeſſion, in conjunction with a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous purſuit after, overtaking of, and being poſſeſſed with Reſt, as we thought, in the <hi>World</hi>) running in the way of <hi>Egypt,</hi> after <hi>Aſher</hi> and <hi>Jareb,</hi> putting Confidence in an Aim of Fleſh, ſaying to the work of our hands, Ye are our gods, when in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning and in Reſt we ſhould have been ſaved, Quietneſs and Confidence ſhould have been our Strength, but we would not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore are we like to be left as a Beacon on the top of the Mountain, our way hedged up with Thorns that we may no more find thoſe Paths, but reduced into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a place of Deſarts, Pits, Drought, and ſhadow of Death; that neceſſity and want of what we would have enjoyed, might we had our wills, may inforce us with the proud Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal, to return to our Father, thankfully accepting what we formerly lightly eſteemed, which his ever-to-be-magnified Grace ſtill holds forth to us, which now we begin to experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the worth of, the Commotions in our Souls being ſtilled, and our prodigal Expectations come to nought, that formerly ſo clamored in our Souls, that the Voice of the Lord could not be heard. Oh how attentive, watchful and diligent are we now, for which formerly we took little notice of, how home, direct and facile is its entrance! Now, ſpeak Lord, ſaith the Soul, and I will hear; appear, and I am ready; lead, and I will follow; command, and I will obey: wee'l never ſay more to the works of our hands, Ye are our gods; for in <hi>Thee</hi> alone the Fatherleſs findeth Mercy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What a large meaſure of Light, Time, Peace and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty have we had from the Lord, beyond what former Times, and, it may be, latter ſhall enjoy, whereby through the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Improvement of which, what manner of Perſons might we have been, not only in our own inward Injoyments and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhips, but alſo to the poor, blind World, captivated by the Devil; as alſo to thoſe who hang in the Birth betwixt Heaven and Hell, that ſee but like the half-cured Blind-man, Men like Trees, that fain would move toward <hi>Sion,</hi> but through the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96479:4"/>weakneſs of their ſight, the falſe Repreſentations of the Devil, together with the Duſt we by our Contentions have raiſed, and darkned the way with, that he knows not how hardly to ſet one foot forward, in order thereto.</p>
            <p>And yet, Oh how too truly may we behold how we have hid our Talent in a Napkin, put our Light under a Buſhel, whilſt we induſtriouſly imployed our Wit and earthly Mind in making proviſion for the Fleſh, merchandizing with the Commodities of this Life, or elſe either exerciſing them in ſuch a cold fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, heartleſs, lifeleſs, cuſtomary manner, that we have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther felt, taſted, nor experienced that Strength, Life, Health and Nouriſhment we might have done, nor by Example, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Converſation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have we ſet others ſo much as we might have done in the way thereto; or, which is worſe, than if we had been born dumb, We have by our time, Light, Knowledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but for the moſt part got ſuch an opinionative Profeſſion, centring in certain external Inſtitutions (being by Chriſt appointed not for Reſt but Motion) which, although ſome of which was perſpicuous enough in the word, yet others being of doubtful Interpretation, have (in the way that ſome have practiſed them) found ſtrong oppoſition; We have ſo ſtudyed and imployed our Abilities thereabouts, that our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the Knowledge of Chriſt hath got from our hearts into our heads, that inſtead of ſweetning our Souls therewith, and refreſhing, enlivening and uniting our Souls to every one in whom the Image of the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> doth appear, thereby upholding that admirable and ever bleſſed <hi>Communion of the Saints</hi> in the <hi>Unity</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> and the <hi>Bond</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> we have (as naturally conſequent thereof) ſo rent the <hi>ſeamleſs</hi> Coat of Chriſt; ſo broken and divided the Saints in pieces; ſo wounded and tortured the Conſciences of the Tender; ſo obſtructed the Goſpels Propagation; ſo rejoyced the World, making the Wicked to triumph, erected ſuch Trophies to the Devil's praiſe, that many have been even Factors for Satan, Fewel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers for Hell, labouring to bring in more matter for the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Burning, under pretence of beating down <hi>Babylon, &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt's <hi>Life</hi> hath been ſtifled, and <hi>Sion</hi> crucified. Oh what a potent deadly Engine of the Devil have we managed, inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96479:4"/>and by unobſerved degrees promoted to many-headed <hi>Babel,</hi> by ſuch as would aſcend into Heaven alone, the language of whoſe Workmen the Lord is now confounding, reducing them into one Common Calamity in order to their Re-unity: The Lord give all his people a Sight, a Sorrow, a Repentance to Amendment, with Pardon for this thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How have we took up our aboad in the Wilderneſs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our hearts, <hi>It's good for us to be here!</hi> Or, upon the diſtruſt of this Security, removed but to the Suburbs of <hi>Sion,</hi> from whence we might either with eaſe, Retire at pleaſure to the old Reſidence, or enjoy them in Common together; reſting in thoſe things, as the <hi>End,</hi> that by Inſtitution was appointed but as a <hi>Mean</hi> thereto. How violent hath been our motion after Air and Emptineſs, whilſt the Eternal Pearl hath ſtood as a thing not worth the laying out our time, ſtrength and induſtry for the obtaining of? How comfortable hath the Intelligence of our likelihood of enjoying the Worlds Felicity been unto our Souls, whilſt thoſe Eternal Enrichments of the Kingdom of Glory have in their moſt powerful and lively Delineations, made upon us ſuch faint Impreſſions, eſteeming and rather chooſing to abide in theſe dirty houſes of Clay, enſlaved to the World, our Souls impriſoned from God, and in our earthly dark mind, which is too much predominant; pore up and down with the poor blind World after Reſt and Felicity in thoſe uncertain things, that have it not in themſelves, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than with Noble, Saint-like Reſolutions, contemn thoſe childiſh <hi>Gew gaws</hi> (that pleaſe but the ſenſitive and moſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble part) and raiſe up our Souls into the apprehenſion of, and purſuit after, and reſtleſs motion, till we are poſſeſſed with thoſe heavenly Treaſures, thoſe durable Riches that give full, comfortable and perpetual Satisfaction; which, till the Soul light upon, and center in, as its End of Motion, Oh how ſad and lamentable (by accident) how deceitful and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is every ſublunary thing that we give our minds to, that we might gain Reſt and Comfort from!</p>
            <p n="5">5. How little did we hearken after, or take delight in the Appearance of the Harbingers and fore-runners of our Lord's Preſence? how little have we been affected with the approach
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96479:5"/>of the Year and Day of our Deliverance, with the Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and fore-thoughts of our purchaſed Poſſeſſion, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Unity and Communion with Chriſt and all Saints in Light; yea, when the Lord hath by the mighty Power of his Spirit in the Mouthes of ſome of his Servants brought theſe Things ſweetly to our Ears, with the danger of Negligence, Key-coldneſs, Formality, and the love of this preſent World, that ſo interpoſeth, eclipſeth and hindreth the Influences of theſe things from our Souls, that they can take neither Life, Strength nor Refreſhment therefrom: How formally, ſleepily and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfully have we given them Entertainment, as things we were not concerned in, or had no need as yet to trouble our ſelves about; yea, even in that very Inſtitution by which Chriſt in what he hath done, is a doing and will ſpeedily do for his Saints, is exhibited and repreſented? How little have we been refreſhed, ſtrengthened, and made watchful to the Day of his Appearance, many rather eating and drinking Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to themſelves? firſt, obſtructing and ſhutting out its Operation from their Souls by their own Unpreparedneſs, and then go away and report that God was not there to be found, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. How ſeldom have we come with hungry and thirſty Souls to, and after the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> whereby we might have expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced the Word of the Lord to have been more reviving and delightful to our taſte than <hi>Honey</hi> and the <hi>Honey-comb,</hi> or any temporal Food to the outward man; and more ſatisfactory, enriching and deſirable than <hi>Gold,</hi> yea, than <hi>much fine Gold?</hi> Oh how oftner rather have we ſo filled and glutted our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites and Affections with <hi>Fleſhly Proviſions,</hi> being rich, full and ſatisfied before-hand with the World, that the <hi>Word of the Lord</hi> hath been but as an empty ſound, which we have only lent our Ears to, going away, poor, empty, miſerable, blind and naked, though we ſee and knew it not!</p>
            <p n="7">7. How common hath it been with us to ſpend much of our time in diſcourſe of the World, our Imployments therein, and trading therewith, our Gains and Loſſe thereby; which, after News from Heaven, our Title thereto, and Intereſt therein, our thriving or loſing in and about thoſe Means of Grace that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96479:5"/>are Aſſiſtants thereabout, in breathing forth our Experience of God's Love, in praiſing the <hi>Lord</hi> for his <hi>admirable Love</hi> to us-ward, when we were in our Blood, in the eſtate of Wrath, Death and Condemnation, ſhut out from the Preſence of <hi>God</hi> into Priſon, Captivity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that then by the precious Blood of the Son of his Love, He ſhould not only ranſom and redeem us therefrom, but by the Power of his Word and Spirit, call us into the inſight thereof, and Everlaſting Reſt, Peace and Comfort thereby; being brought into the Arms and Boſom of himſelf, and made Heirs of Eternal Glory; alſo, in magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Mercy to us-ward, in reſtraining the Power of <hi>Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men,</hi> from exerciſing their Cruelty upon us, who would have devoured us quick, whom yet the Lord would not ſuffer, but was a brazen Wall round about us, that we might have gone freely about the work of our God without moleſtation; to have enlightned the eyes of the poor blind World, enlivened, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſtrengthened the weak Saints, confirmed the Feeble, and rejoyced in and with the Strong; in laying in all ſtrength together, with one heart and one ſhoulder, to bear up, increaſe and ſtrengthen the Kingdom of the Lord Jeſus; rejoycing with the Strong and Honourable, and weeping with the Poor and Miſerable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beating with the Weak and Feeble; and, as Members of one Body, joyned together, and compacted by that which every Joynt ſupplyeth, according to the <hi>Effectual working</hi> in the meaſure of every part, <hi>making increaſe in the Body unto the Edifying of it ſelf in Love.</hi> Oh! how negligent have we been in theſe neceſſary heavenly Duties, bearing the name of <hi>Churches, Saints</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> when to the Life of Chriſt we have been almoſt ſtrangers!</p>
            <p n="8">8. How little have our hearts been rent, our ſouls grieved, and we ſighed and cryed, pouring out our ſouls before the Lord for the Abominations committed in theſe Nations, not being inferiour, if not exceeding the Wickedneſs of <hi>Sodom,</hi> for, and on which God rained down from Heaven <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> and made an utter deſolation thereof! How is the <hi>Name</hi> of our God every day <hi>blasphemed,</hi> his <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>gracious Precepts derided,</hi> and his <hi>People ſhamefully entreated;</hi> and, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96479:6"/>ſaid of the Times ſome late years paſt, <hi>That it was as much as a Mans Eſtate at leaſt was worth to hear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Saints Reſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 251. <hi>Part</hi> 2.</note>
               <hi>a Sermon abroad, when he had none, or worſe, at home; to meet for Prayer, or any godly Exerciſe; and that it was a matter of Credit, and way to Preferment, to revile at, and be enemies to thoſe that are moſt Conſciencious; and every where ſafer to be a Drunkard, or an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer, than a painful Chriſtian; and that multitude of humane Ceremonies took place, when the Worſhip of Chriſts Inſtitutions was caſt out!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So, by reaſon of the abuſe of the <hi>King's Indulgence,</hi> of about Thirty Perſons, whom in that we had no compliance with, nor knowledge of, together with the over-violent activity of his Majeſties ſubordinate Miniſters in executing of his <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> againſt us (though we believe they know in their own Conſciences we are free from the <hi>firſt,</hi> and conſequently not concerned in the <hi>laſt</hi>) with their negligence, in not executing his <hi>Proclamation</hi> againſt <hi>Debauchery</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs;</hi> ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many places having free liberty to act Villany: It's come to that paſſe, that if a few ſincere Chriſtians meet together <hi>in the fear of God,</hi> to <hi>build up one another in their moſt holy Faith;</hi> to <hi>exhort, comfort, confirm</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> each other in the <hi>Wayes of God,</hi> according to the <hi>Command of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Example</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Saints;</hi> to which Work the Lord having promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and God's People ſweetly experiencing his Preſence; We muſt be <hi>preſently apprehended,</hi> and carried to a <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Jayl;</hi> yea, ſome of us <hi>threatned</hi> for <hi>reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in our Families;</hi> when if we would <hi>ſwear, game,</hi> be <hi>drunk,</hi> and lie at an <hi>Alehouſe, Twenty together day after day,</hi> or ſtand in a Market an hour or two together, to hear the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Factors</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> about and on the <hi>Market-Croſs,</hi> with their <hi>Ungodly Songs</hi> and <hi>Speeches,</hi> and <hi>idle, ſhameful Deeds</hi> and <hi>Geſtures,</hi> to provoke to <hi>vanity,</hi> both <hi>Hearers, Speakers</hi> and <hi>Singers,</hi> ſhall have <hi>free Liberty;</hi> when if in the ſame place, (as ſome with grief of heart can witneſs) one doth but ſay, <hi>[Repent of this Folly, and turn to the Lord, His Day is at hand]</hi> he ſhall have company about him preſently to <hi>lag</hi> him forth of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96479:6"/>Town, as not ſufferable therein; Which had it been amongſt <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>groſs Heathens,</hi> we might have the leſs marvelled; but to ſee it amongſt thoſe, that profeſs in words to be <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians:</hi> Oh! what Lamentations, bitter Cryes, Sighes and Tears, and heart-rendings doth this call for! what Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Watchings, Faſtings, Prayings, Speakings often one to another, and to the Lord, <hi>to forgive, to ſtrengthen, uphold</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> his People in this day; and to <hi>Inform, counſel</hi> and <hi>direct</hi> the King, with the Magiſtrates of this Nation, in the performance of that which may bring down a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and a <hi>Settlement</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> with <hi>Truth</hi> thereby, and that they may ſee in what the <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of a Nation ſtands in; In the <hi>performance</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs, Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity; breaking every heavy Yoak,</hi> and <hi>letting the Oppreſſed go free;</hi> in <hi>ſetting free</hi> the <hi>Gospel</hi> and the <hi>VVord of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors thereof,</hi> (that hath ſo long been confined within the narrow limits of ſome mens particular Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) that it <hi>may run</hi> and <hi>be glorified,</hi> and <hi>prevail</hi> and <hi>prosper</hi> in its own <hi>ſingle Evidence;</hi> and that the Lord would cauſe them to ſee the <hi>Hamon</hi>-like Deſigns that ſome <hi>purpoſe</hi> againſt <hi>all the Sons of Sion,</hi> that <hi>refuſe</hi> to <hi>bow</hi> to the <hi>Pride</hi> of their <hi>Hearts;</hi> and that the <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Lords People</hi> may be brought to light, in <hi>despight</hi> of thoſe <hi>wicked Ones,</hi> who ſeek to impeach and darken it; that ſo their Covering may not prove like that of <hi>Judah</hi>'s, In <hi>looking to their Armour,</hi> and <hi>making up the Breaches,</hi> and <hi>fortifying of the Walls, ſtaying on Horſes,</hi> and <hi>truſting in Chariots, becauſe they are many,</hi> and <hi>in Horſemen, becauſe they are very ſtrong;</hi> and then <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>be glad, ſlay Oxen,</hi> and <hi>kill Sheep, eat Fleſh</hi> and <hi>drink Wine,</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all ſecure; when they ſhould rather <hi>call to Mourning,</hi> to <hi>Weeping,</hi> to <hi>Baldneſs,</hi> and <hi>to girding with Sackcloath,</hi> if the Glory of the Lord and the ſaving ſtrength of himſelf, be not the Foundation thereof, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.8.—14.31.1.</p>
            <p>Oh! how little have we been ſenſible of, affected with, and imployed about theſe things? though the Lord hath neither been a Wilderneſs nor a Land of Darkneſs to us, but planting us a <hi>Noble Vine,</hi> a <hi>holy,</hi> a <hi>right Seed,</hi> walling us about, ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no man to do us harm; yet have we <hi>degenerated into a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96479:7"/>ſtrange Plant;</hi> our <hi>Silver</hi> become <hi>Droſs,</hi> our <hi>Wine mixt with Water,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore <hi>the Day of Viſitation is come, it is come,</hi> we ſhall know it: We have dealt <hi>treacherouſly</hi> with the Lord, we have <hi>begotten ſtrange Children:</hi> now ſhall a Moth <hi>devour them with their Portions;</hi> for, <hi>the Lord is ariſen in the fury of his Jealouſie,</hi> being <hi>provoked</hi> through the <hi>abuſe of his Mercy,</hi> to <hi>laſh</hi> us to himſelf, and <hi>correct us</hi> for our <hi>out-goings</hi> from his Grace, and hath prepared his <hi>Furnace</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and his <hi>Refining Pot</hi> in <hi>Sion;</hi> in which <hi>two parts</hi> may be conſumed, and a <hi>third</hi> brought through the fire; being thereby made meet for our Maſters praiſe, we may ſerve him with one conſent.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, <hi>dearly beloved Brethren,</hi> you who <hi>Fellow-Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens,</hi> and of the <hi>Houſhold of God, Members one of another, One Body, of which Chriſt is the Head; Children and Heirs, Heirs of God,</hi> yea <hi>Joynt-heirs with Chriſt;</hi> and all <hi>Strangers and Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims</hi> here on Earth, having <hi>no continuing City, but are looking after one that hath a foundation, whoſe maker and builder is God, &amp;c.</hi> Let's lay aſide our <hi>dividing Principles,</hi> and <hi>formal, lazy, key-cold Profeſſion,</hi> and <hi>Unchriſtian-like Imployments,</hi> and with <hi>one Conſent</hi> make exact and ſpeedy ſearch into <hi>thoſe things</hi> in which we have grievouſly <hi>offended,</hi> and pour forth our <hi>ſouls</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Lord,</hi> Repenting and humbling our ſelves, and that with all ſpeed; Peradventure we may prevail to a <hi>diverſion</hi> of God's intended <hi>Judgments</hi> againſt us; if not, that then they may be of excellent uſe to us: for when we have once ſeen the want of that, which when we had, we ſaw not the worth of, nor had no hearts to uſe; It will then be more precious in our eyes, more deſirable and delightful to our ſouls; Should the Lord <hi>ſcatter</hi> us abroad into other Nations, to <hi>wander</hi> up and down amongſt <hi>Mountains, Deſarts, Dens, Caves,</hi> and <hi>Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late places of the Earth,</hi> deſtitute, afflicted and tormented; yea, from <hi>Sea</hi> to <hi>Sea,</hi> from <hi>North</hi> to <hi>South, running to and fro to ſeck the Word of the Lord, and ſhall not find it;</hi> Oh how <hi>precious</hi> would the <hi>Communion,</hi> the <hi>Company,</hi> the <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> of thoſe be then, notwithſtanding circumſtantial difference, with whom now we have been at Irreconciliable Variance! how delightful that Preſence of the Lord that once we enjoyed in his <hi>Sanctuary!</hi> how piercing and lively would the fence of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96479:7"/>thoſe former <hi>neglected Mercies</hi> come freſh and bleeding in our memories! how <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> would the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> be to our hungry, ſtarved, empty Souls then! how <hi>vivifying</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable</hi> to our Hearts, though now being full, we <hi>loath the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and the Honey-comb!</hi> how little ſhould we value a weeks time then, in the performance of that, which a dayes time now hath wearied us in! how <hi>near</hi> would our Hearts be brought <hi>to God,</hi> our Affections <hi>to Heaven,</hi> and <hi>from</hi> the <hi>World!</hi> how <hi>un-interrupted</hi> the courſe of our <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>crucified</hi> to the <hi>Pleaſures</hi> of this <hi>Life!</hi> how <hi>deſirous</hi> to <hi>be diſſolved,</hi> how <hi>pained</hi> to be <hi>delivered!</hi> how <hi>watchful</hi> for our <hi>Redemption,</hi> and <hi>Day</hi> of our <hi>Lord's Appearance!</hi> how <hi>attentive</hi> to our <hi>main work,</hi> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our <hi>wedding Garment!</hi> how <hi>quick</hi> in our <hi>motion,</hi> and <hi>ſteady</hi> in our <hi>expectation,</hi> looking right on, moving <hi>regular</hi> in our Journey, turning neither to the <hi>right hand,</hi> nor to the <hi>left! &amp;c.</hi> Should we then be, when the Lord with a Witneſs hath diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and uncovered our Covering, which He is now about, and hunted us out of our Reſts, that were polluted, and would have deſtroyed us with a ſore deſtruction, and ſcorched us with the fire of our own kindling, and made thoſe ſparks we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed our ſelves about with, and walk'd in the light of, like thoſe Oaks we have deſired, of which we are now aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, going away from them, the Lord having rejected that Confidence which we put in them.</p>
            <p>How admirably lovely and deſirable will Chriſt, his Truth and Kingdom be, when it ſtands in competition with Goods, Liberty, Wife, Children, and it may be our own Life alſo, when we ſhall be brought to that parting-point, to receive Him ſingly, or reject Him wholly, Then will be the time to ſee the worth of that, which whilſt other things ſtood betwixt, we ſaw not the full glory of! Oh then let's not fear, nor be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed at that which, if rightly uſed, we ſhall be ſuch gainers by, but rejoyce, and leap for Joy, in that Day when men ſhall <hi>hate us, impriſon us, ſeparate us</hi> from their <hi>Company,</hi> and <hi>ſpeak all manner of evil of us falſly,</hi> and take away our <hi>Goods,</hi> our <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Lands,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> from us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For if we ſtoop under the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and <hi>deny</hi> our ſelves, and forſake <hi>Houſes, Brethren, Siſters, Fathers</hi> or <hi>Mothers, VVife</hi> or <hi>Children,</hi> or <hi>Lands for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96479:8"/>the Name ſake of Chriſt, we ſhall receive un hundred fold, and ſhall inherit Everlaſting Life,</hi> Matth. 19.29. Only let's be careful to <hi>ſuffer</hi> as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> not as <hi>Thieves, Murderers, buſie bodies in others matters, ſelf-revengers, &amp;c.</hi> for which we ſhall have a double puniſhment; but if as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> let's not be aſhamed, <hi>but glorifie God on this behalf, and commit the keeping of our ſouls in wel-doing as to a faithful Creator;</hi> Conſidering Him that could have called for the Hoſt of Heaven to have <hi>reſcued</hi> Him, and <hi>avenged</hi> Him of his Enemies; yet <hi>endured the Croſs, despiſed the ſhame,</hi> and the <hi>Contradiction of Sinners againſt Himſelf,</hi> and <hi>is ſet down at the right-hand of God, expecting till his Enemies be made his Footſtool:</hi> And let us not envy the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity</hi> of them that know not God, that <hi>laugh</hi> whilſt we <hi>weep,</hi> and <hi>ſing</hi> whilſt <hi>we mourn;</hi> for they have received their Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and are in the flower of their Kingdom; but ours is in Reverſion, which when we come to the poſſeſſion of, out <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> ſhall be turned into <hi>Joy,</hi> our <hi>Tears</hi> to <hi>Praiſe,</hi> our <hi>Poverty</hi> to <hi>Plenty,</hi> and we ſhall come to <hi>Sion</hi> with <hi>Songs,</hi> and <hi>Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Joy upon our heads; Sorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away, when we ſhall be made an Eternal Excellency, the Joy of many Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> For, behold, <hi>the Lord will take out of our hand the Cup of Trembling, even the Dregs of the Cup of Fury we ſhall no more drink, but it ſhall be put into the hand of them that afflict us, that have ſaid to our ſouls, Bow down, that we may go over; And we have laid our body as the ground, and as the ſtreet to them that went over; when he hath purged away our Droſs, and performed his whole work upon us, He will extend Peace to us like a River, and Judgment ſhall dwell in the VVilderneſs, and Righteouſneſs remain in the fruitful Field; and the work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the effect of Righteouſneſs Quietneſs and Aſſurance for ever:</hi> Which when we ſee, our hearts ſhall rejoyce, and our bones flouriſh, and we ſhall diſcern the difference betwixt them that <hi>ſerve God,</hi> and them that <hi>ſerve Him not;</hi> though now <hi>the Proud are called Happy, &amp;c.</hi> The hand of the Lord will be known to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his Servants, and his Indignation toward his Enemies, <hi>when he ſhall render his Anger with Fury, and his Rebukes with flames of fire. For, behold, the day cometh that ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the Proud,</hi> yea, <hi>and all that do wickedly ſhall be as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96479:8"/>Stubble, and the day that cometh ſhall burn them up, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> that it ſhall leave them neither <hi>root</hi> nor <hi>branch; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in flaming Fire will He take Vengeance on all that know not God, and obey not the Gospel of Jeſus Chriſt: For, behold, He co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with Ten Thouſand of his Saints, to execute Judgment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly amongst them, of all their ungodly deeds, they have ungodlily committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have spoken againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore let us enter into our Chamber, and ſhut to the doors, till the Indignation of the Lord lie over-paſt, and bear it with patience, for we have ſinned; and gird up the loyns of our mind and be ſober, and hope to the end; and take up the Croſs and walk on with patience, <hi>lifting up our hands that hang down, and making ſtrait paths for our feet; lest that which is lame be turned out of the way, and run with patience the Race ſet before us,</hi> not being mindful of that Country from whence we came out, though we may have opportunity to return, <hi>[Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Lots Wife]</hi> but deſire a better, that is, an <hi>heavenly;</hi> And God will not be aſhamed to be called our God, for he hath provided for us a City: and let us not draw back, leſt the Lord take no pleaſure in us: for, <hi>he that ſeeks to ſave his life, ſhall loſe it, whilst he that ſeeks to loſe it ſhall find.</hi> Let's not then caſt away our Confidence, that hath great Recompence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; for we have need of Patience, that after we have done the Will of God, we may receive the Promiſe: <hi>For yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry: whoſe Reward is with him, and his Work before him, to give to every one as his deeds ſhall be.</hi> In the Expectation of which, and waiting therefore, I am, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Brother in the Faith, Patience, and Tribulation of the Gospel,</hi> John Onley.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>3d day of the 3d Month, 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
